Guide to the Norman Douglas Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- 1993-2003 Acquisitions, circa 1930-1952; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Additions 1995-2003, Series III
    - Oriolo, Giuseppe
      - Portrait of Norman Douglas taken by Carl Van Vechten, undated; 1 item. (Box 43, Folder 19)
        Autographed "For Hester and David with love from Pino, 1936."
      - Portrait of Pino Orioli and cat, [1936]; 1 item. (Box 43, Folder 20)
        Autographed "Best wishes from Pino and his tiger." With snapshot of Norman Douglas and Pino Orioli.
    - Douglas, Norman
      - Letter: via Tornabuoni, Florence, to Pat Lawlor, 1936 July 19; 1 item (1 leaf); 27 cm. (Box 43, Folder 21)
        Autograph letter signed to Pat Lawlor making appointment. With: envelope.
      - "The Last Word," holograph corrected, signed, bound, [circa 1924]; 1 v. (16 p.); 28 cm. (Box 43, Folder 22)
        Manuscript of the revised short story as it appeared in Experiments (1925).
        Bound with: printed pages of the same text.
        Bound in purple morocco.
      - Letter: The English Review, 17-21, Tavistock Street, Covent Garden, London, W.C., to Henry Savage, 1913 March 4; 1 item (1 L.); 20 cm. (Box 43, Folder 23)
        Autograph letter signed concerning Mr. Harrison's business with Savage and Douglas.
        Purchased in 1999.
        Acc: 990820-d
      - Letter: Thomas Cook, via Tornabuoni, Florence, to W. B. Button, 1926 October 20; 1 item (1 L.); 27 cm. (Box 43, Folder 24)
        Autograph letter signed to Button about a shipment of books. With: envelope.
      - Photograph of Norman Douglas's birthplace in Thüringen, [2000]; 1 item; 10 cm. x 15 cm. (Box 43, Folder 25)
        Color photograph of the house in which Norman Douglas was born. Annotated: "The first 12 years of his childhood he spent in this house."
        Acc: 20000816-l
      - Letter: to John Mavrogordato, 1946 Jun 15; 1 item; 26 cm. (Box 43, Folder 26)
        Autograph letter signed thanking him for a pipe and mentioning a book sent and an enclosure (not present). With: envelope.
        Purchased in 2002.
        Acc: 20020723-j
      - Together, [1922?]; 3 items. (Box 43, Folder 27)
        Manuscript, corrected and annotated, bound; manuscript notebook of index; typescript, corrected, of index. Manuscript inscribed to "his friend Mr. R." by ND. Bookplate: Norman Douglas.
        Purchased in 2003.
        Acc: 20030416-d
      - Letters: to Montgomery Evans, 1925-1946, undated; 18 items. (Box 43, Folder 28)
        15 autograph letters signed, 1 typescript letter signed, 1 autograph postcard signed and 1 endorsed check.
        Subjects include sales of books, proofs and manuscripts by Douglas to Evans; plans for visits by Douglas; and travel news. With: autograph letter signed to Robin Douglas, 1929 October 23, offering advice on writing. Accompanied by typed transcripts. With: TLS to Mr. Johnson, 1928 October 27. With: 15 envelopes.
        Acc: 20030416-e
- January 2008 Acquisition, circa 1900-1971; Series III; 8.83; (15 boxes) + 1 art
  The January 2008 Acquisition is organized into four series: I. Norman Douglas Papers. II. Maurice Magnus Papers. III. Kenneth Macpherson Papers. IV. Islay de Courcy Lyons Papers. This organization is based on the order in which the material was received by the library.
  The January 2008 Acquisition contains material created and accumulated by Norman Douglas, Maurice Magnus, Kenneth Macpherson, and Islay de Courcy Lyons. Material includes correspondence, writings, photographs, photograph albums, financial and business papers, printed material, and a sculpture, which document aspects of Douglas's writing career as well as his relationships with other writers and artists.
  Formerly classed as GEN MSS 614.
  - Norman Douglas Papers, Series I
    Organized into six subseries: Writings; Notebooks and Photographs; Correspondence; Personal Effects; Royalty Statements and Publishing Contracts; and Printed Material.
    This arrangement is based on the order in which the material was received by the library. Unless otherwise noted, files within each subseries have been kept in the order in which they were received.
    - Writings
      - "The Brigands' Forest", typescript, undated (Box 44)
      - "Index", typescript, undated (Box 44)
      - "An Almanac", bound proof, 1945 March 27 (Box 44)
      - "Venus in the Kitchen", typescript, undated (Box 44)
      - "ND: Almanac: Version Corrected for Press", typescript, undated (Box 44)
      - "Birds and Beasts etc/Corrected", typescript, 1926 (Box 44)
      - "Paneros", proofs, undated (Box 44)
      - "Occhietto", proofs, undated (Box 44)
      - "Author's Note" and holograph, undated (Box 44)
      - Douglas Goldring article, galley proofs, 1954 May 29, undated (Box 44)
      - "The Blue Grotto and its Literature", proofs, circa 1930s (Box 44)
        Contains proofs of "The Forestal Conditions of Capri" and "Fabio Giordano's Relation of Capri".
      - "The 'Unredeemed' Countries" by Nicola Pascazio, galley proofs, undated (Box 44)
        Contains typescript of "Teremoto" by Conte Giancinto Cottini.
      - "Creeping Things", typescript, undated (Box 44)
      - "In the Beginning / ND / Original 27 Drawings: Designs / Title Page / Charles Cullen", undated (Box 44)
    - Notebooks and Photographs
      - "1901 and 1902 Reminiscences", notebook, circa 1900s (Box 44)
        Notebook contains flower pressings.
      - "A" and "B" notebooks, regarding Capri, undated (Box 44)
      - "C" and "D" notebooks, regarding Capri, Italy and Naples., undated (Box 44)
      - "Sant' Angelo / Photos of Old Calabria", circa 1911 (Box 44)
      - Islay Lyons photographs of Norman Douglas and others., circa 1948-1952; 2 folders (Box 44)
      - Islay Lyons photographs of Norman Douglas and others., circa 1948-1952; 5 folders (Box 45)
      - Islay Lyons photographic negatives and proofs, undated (Box 45)
      - Norman Douglas photographs, by Cecil Beaton, undated (Box 45)
      - Norman Douglas photographs, by Carl van Vechten, circa 1935 (Box 45)
      - Photographs of Norman Douglas, circa 1930s-1950s; 3 folders (Box 45)
      - Photographs of Italian scenes, undated (Box 45)
        Contains two gravure photographs of Norman Douglas by Robert Davis.
      - "Old Cemetery at Rome - 1867" with photographs of maps and negatives, 1867, undated (Box 45)
    - Correspondence
      Correspondence has been arranged alphabetically by correspondent or subject. Other material is filed at the end.
      - "A" General, 1942 (Box 45)
      - "B" General, 1908-1947, undated (Box 45)
      - Bryher, 1937-1948 (Box 45)
      - "C" General, 1901-1949, undated (Box 45)
      - Chatto & Windus, 1938, 1946-49 (Box 45)
      - Crutch, Mrs. Gordon, 1934-1935 (Box 45)
      - "D" General, 1942-1948 (Box 45)
      - De Filippi, Amedeo, 1948-1951; 2 folders (Box 45)
      - "E" General, 1942-1947 (Box 45)
      - Freaks, 1924-1931, undated (Box 45)
      - Frere, A.S., 1951 (Box 45)
      - "G" General, 1937-1947 (Box 45)
      - Greene, Graham, 1951 (Box 45)
      - "H" General, 1940-1947 (Box 45)
      - Harvard Universiy Library, 1926, 1948-1949 (Box 45)
      - Herring, Robert, 1948 (Box 45)
      - Johnson, A.F., 1947 November 10 (Box 45)
        Includes a typed bibliography of works by Douglas.
      - "K" General, undated (Box 45)
      - King, Willie, 1948-1951 (Box 45)
      - Knapp-Fisher, J.S., 1950 (Box 45)
      - "L" General, 1907, 1944-1948 (Box 45)
      - Legal Correspondence, circa 1946-1947
        - Driberg, Tom (Hon.), 1947 (Box 45)
        - Letters to/from attorneys re: apartment in Florence, 1946-1947 (Box 45)
        - Documents relating to settlement of claims concerning confiscation of apartment and property in Florence, 1947 (Box 45)
        - Letters relating to the settlement of claims for confiscation of property and books in Florence, 1946-1947; 2 folders (Box 45)
      - "M" General, 1942, 1947, undated (Box 45)
      - Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 45)
      - Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 45)
      - Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 45)
      - "N" General, undated (Box 45)
      - "O" General, 1937 July 3 (Box 45)
      - The Obelisk Press, 1939-1940 (Box 45)
      - Old Calabria Letters, 1904-1929 (Box 45)
      - "P" General, 1942, 1947 (Box 45)
      - Penguin Books Ltd. (A.S.B. Glover and others), circa 1944-1947 (Box 45)
      - Pitkin, M.I., 1948 (Box 45)
      - Popkin, Percy, 1943-1951, undated (Box 45)
      - "R" General, 1929-1947, undated (Box 45)
      - Raymond, Harold, 1944 (Box 45)
      - "S" General, 1942-1947 (Box 45)
      - Senhouse, Roger, 1937-1949 (Box 45)
      - Society of Authors, 1946, 1950 (Box 45)
      - "South Wind"
        Includes correspondence relating to Douglas's book, South Wind.
        - Correspondence, circa 1920-1939 (Box 45)
        - Liverright, Horace, 1924-1925 (Box 45)
        - Cerf, Bennett, 1926-1936 (Box 45)
        - Society of Authors, 1932-1949; 2 folders (Box 45)
        - Correspondence, circa 1947-1948 (Box 45)
      - "T" General, 1937-1949, undated (Box 46)
      - Temple, Phillips, 1951 (Box 46)
      - Thompson, L.C., 1948 (Box 46)
      - "V" General, 1946-1947 (Box 46)
      - Vallese, Tarquinio, 1948-1949 (Box 46)
      - "W" General, 1947-1948 (Box 46)
      - Wolton, Eric, 1946 (Box 46)
      - _______, Emilio, 1945-1948 (Box 46)
      - Unidentified, 1942-1950, undated (Box 46)
      - Notes from Norman Douglas, 1947 (Box 46)
      - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, 1938, undated (Box 46)
      - "Holograph Listing", undated (Box 46)
    - Personal Effects
      - Cigar Box and pipe, undated (Box 59)
      - Receipts from Florence taxing authorities, circa 1929-1936 (Box 46)
      - Calling Cards, undated; 2 folders (Box 46)
        Includes approximately five hundred calling cards from Harold Acton, Richard Aldington, Vernon Andrews, Joseph Conrad, Bennett Cerf, Booth Tarkington, Edwin Cerio, Edouard Chimot, Ian Greenlees, Adelsward Fersen, Edward Hutton, Baron Imhoff, Ford Madox Hueffer, Edmund John, Walter Lownfels, John Mavrocordato, Duca di Montecalvo, Axel Munthe, Scott Moncrieff, Harold Trower, H.M. Tomlinson, William Wordsworth and others.
    - Royalty Statements and Publishing Contracts
      - Martin Secker & Warburg Ltd., royalty statements, circa 1937-1949 (Box 46)
      - Dodd, Mead & Co., royalty statements, circa 1937-1949 (Box 46)
      - Chatto & Windus, royalty statements, circa 1937-1950 (Box 46)
      - Lindsay Drummon Ltd., "Late Harvest" royalties, circa 1947-1948 (Box 46)
      - Society of Authors, royalty statements, circa 1937-1951 (Box 46)
      - Boni & Liveright and Modern Library, "South Wind" royalties, circa 1925-1930 (Box 46)
      - Secker & Warburg, "Siren Lady" and "Fountains in the Sand" royaties, circa 1942-1951 (Box 46)
        Contains statements and letters from Hughes Massie & Co, regarding royalties.
      - Publishing Contracts, circa 1910-1951 (Box 46)
    - Printed Material
      - "South Wind" clippings and theatre programs, circa 1923 (Box 46)
      - Italian clippings and "Eve" clippings, circa 1920s (Box 46)
      - Newspaper clippings regarding "Looking Back", circa 1933 (Box 46)
      - Miscellaneous Publications and clippings, circa 1914-1959; 2 folders (Box 46)
  - Maurice Magnus papers, Series II
    - "Maurice Magnus / Literary Relics", notebook, undated (Box 47)
    - "For Roman Review. Material to be used & used", circa 1917-1919 (Box 47)
    - Typescripts, with correspondence, 1915-1916, undated (Box 47)
    - Typescripts, with proofs, 1916-1918, undated (Box 47)
  - Kenneth Macpherson papers, Series III
    Organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Other Papers, and Sculpture.
    - Correspondence
      - Berman, Eugene, 1959-1962 (Box 47)
      - Douglas, Archibald (Incoming), 1952-1957; 2 folders (Box 47)
      - Douglas, Archibald (Outgoing), 1952-1957 (Box 47)
      - Douglas Archibald to Robin Douglas (Carbons), 1952 (Box 47)
      - Douglas, Norman, 1938-1943 (Box 47)
      - Douglas, Robin, 1952-1957; 4 folders (Box 47)
      - Douglas, Robin to and from Archibald Douglas and others, 1952-1957; 2 folders (Box 47)
      - "Chamber of Horrors or My White Paper. A Symposium of Beauty, Gratitude, Gentleness, Filial and Paternal Love, and of the Qualities of Faithful Friendship. Italy, January 1952" (Box 47)
        Includes letters from Norman Douglas to Archibald Douglas, and from Robin Douglas to Kenneth MacPherson and Islay de Courcy Lyons, compiled in a folder and titled by MacPherson.
      - Munro-Kerr, Ann (Society of Authors), 1967, 1970 (Box 47)
      - Correspondence relating to book about Norman Douglas and other publishing projects, 1952-1955 (Box 47)
      - Correspondence regarding Norman Douglas Estate, 1953-1955 (Box 47)
      - "General Statement of Account of Norman Douglas. In Respect of his Capri Estate.", 1952 (Box 47)
      - Papers regarding death of Norman Douglas, 1952-1975 (Box 47)
        Includes handwritten notes from Norman Douglas to Kenneth MacPherson, including his suicide note; correspondence between Islay de Courcy Lyons and Mark Holloway regarding the last days of Norman Douglas; and typescript by Lyons entitled "Constantine Fitzgibbon's Memoir of an Unwritten Biography of Norman Douglas."
      - Correspondence, Various, 1958-1968 (Box 47)
    - Writings
      - "Original Manuscript of Capri Manuscript", typescript, undated (Box 47)
      - Nancy Cunard typescript relating to book project on Norman Douglas, 1953-1954 (Box 47)
      - "Omnes Eodem Cogimur", 1952 March (Box 47)
      - "To Feed a Hoopoe" by Kenneth Macpherson, typescript, undated (Box 47)
    - Other Papers
      - Leather guest book, 1947-1948 (Box 47)
      - "Guest book of Villa Tuoro Capri", 1949-1952 (Box 47)
      - Villa Tuoro photograph album, circa 1950 (Box 47)
      - Scrapbook containing photo collages of Black subjects, inscribed to Kenneth MacPherson by Bryher on the first page, circa 1930 (Box 47)
    - Sculpture
      - Bronze bust of Kenneth Macpherson by Richmond Barthé, undated (Box 60 (Art))
  - Islay de Courcy Lyons papers, Series IV
    Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Other Papers, and Photographs.
    - Correspondence and Other Papers
      - Personal correspondence, 1947-1971 (Box 48)
      - Publisher reproduction requests, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 48)
      - Intimate correspondence and "The Photograph", 1946-1947, undated (Box 48)
      - Various literary efforts by Islay Lyons, 1940-1957, undated (Box 48)
      - "Into the Frying Pan", autobiography of Algernon Lyons (Islay), undated; 2 folders (Box 48)
    - Photographs
      - Islay Lyons photographs of various subjects, undated; 7 folders (Box 48)
      - Mary McCarthy, undated (Box 48)
      - Sandy and Kim Veit, 1958 (Box 48)
      - Cecil Grey, undated (Box 48)
      - Gracie Fields, undated (Box 48)
      - Janet Flanner, undated (Box 48)
      - Sir Harold Acton, undated (Box 48)
      - Norman Douglas and Somerset Maugham, undated (Box 48)
      - Sybille Bedford and friend, undated (Box 48)
      - Dottoressa Moor, undated (Box 48)
      - Hilda Doolittle (H.D.), undated (Box 48)
      - Nancy Cunard, undated (Box 48)
      - John Updike, undated (Box 48)
      - Graham Greene and others, undated (Box 48)
      - Cole Porter, undated (Box 48)
      - Landscape and portraits in Capri and Italy, undated; 2 folders (Box 49)
      - "Footnote on Capri", bound maquette, circa 1950s (Box 52 (Oversize))
      - Photographs of Italian scenes and statuary, undated (Box 51)
      - Photographs of Roman scenes and India, undated
      - "Decoration" (Box 49)
      - "Portraits 3", undated (Box 49)
      - Bryher and Kenneth Macpherson, undated (Box 49)
      - Indian statuary, undated (Box 49)
      - Roman cityscapes, undated (Box 53 (Oversize))
      - "Very Special Persons", undated (Box 53 (Oversize))
        Contains photographs of cats and dogs, as well as the original black portfolio.
      - "San Teodoro", undated (Box 49)
      - Kenneth Macpherson, undated; 3 folders (Box 49)
      - Villa Tuoro in Capri, undated; 3 folders (Box 49)
      - Aniene Valley, Ischia, S. Fillippo and Anticoli, undated; 2 folders (Box 49)
      - Photos of Capri, undated; 2 folders (Box 49)
      - Photographs of Rome and environs, circa 1950s (Box 54 (Oversize))
      - Photographs. Northern India, undated
      - Snapshots, negatives and proof sheets, undated (Box 49)
      - Extraordinary Women, photo album, undated (Box 58 (Oversize))
      - Gandaharian Art in Pakistan, undated; 7 folders (Box 50)
  - Oversize Material
    - Miscellaneous Publications and clippings, 1916-1959 (Box 51)
    - Islay Lyons photograph, undated (Box 51)
    - Landscape and portraits in Capri and Italy, undated (Box 51)
    - Photographs of Italian scenes and statuary, undated (Box 51)
    - Photographs of Roman scenes and India, undated (Box 51)
    - Photographs, Northern India, undated (Box 55)
    - Gandaharian Art in Pakistan, undated (Box 55)
    - Gandaharian Art in Pakistan, undated (Box 56)
    - Gandaharian Art in Pakistan, undated (Box 57)
- August 2008 Acquisition, circa 1910s-1980s; Series IV; 2.16; (4 boxes)
  Organized in three series: I. Photographs; II. Letters; and III. Islay Lyons Personal Papers.
  IV. August 2008 Acquisition is comprised primarily of photographs documenting the personal lives and relationships of Norman Douglas, Kenneth Macpherson, Bryher, Islay de Courcy Lyons and others. A small amount of Lyons correspondence and personal papers are also included in this group of material. Two small notebooks in the hand of Lyons document the personal relationships and conversations in this circle of friends during the 1940s, and contain sketches by Lyons.
  - Photographs, Series I
    - "K's Own Collection of Snaps"
      - Bryher, circa 1910-1970s (Box 61)
      - Norman Douglas, Kenneth Macpherson, and Islay Lyons with assorted family and friends, 1930s-1960s, undated; 5 folders (Box 61)
      - Spitzbergen, 1930s (Box 61)
    - Norman Douglas and Pino Orioli in Calabria and Italy, circa 1930s (Box 61)
    - Norman Douglas and W. S. Maugham, photographs and negatives by Islay Lyons, undated (Box 61)
    - Islay Lyons Travel photography of Thailand and India
      - Negatives and prints, black and white and color, 1975-1978; 6 folders (Box 61)
      - Negatives and prints, black and white and color, 1975-1978 (Box 62)
      - Negatives and prints, black and white and color, 1975-1978 (Box 63)
      - Proof sheets and negatives, black and white and color, 1975-1978; 8 folders (Box 61)
    - Assorted photographs, black and white and color, undated (Box 61)
      Includes Islay Lyons, Kenneth Macpherson, Cecil Gray, Richard Mason, Anthony Armstrong-Jones and others.
  - Letters, Series II
    - Lyons, Islay, incoming correspondence regarding permissions to publish photographs; also includes check stubs, receipts, and notes, 1941-1980 (Box 61)
    - Lyons, Islay, typescript original and carbon copies of letters to Richard Mason with typescript diary entries, 1946 (Box 61)
  - Islay de Courcy Lyons Personal Papers, Series III
    - Royal Air Force identification card, automobile licenses from India and Italy, 1946-1974 (Box 61)
    - Notebook in the hand of Islay Lyons, with some entries in the hand of Kenneth Macpherson, 76 pages, circa 1943-1948 (Box 61)
      Includes references to Norman Douglas, Peggy Guggenheim, Gertrude Stein, Ezra Pound, Graham Greene and others. Primarily describes conversations among circle of friends and includes pencil sketches throughout.
    - Notebook in the hand of Islay Lyons with loose notes, 50 pages, undated (Box 61)
      Includes references to Norman Douglas, W. S. Maugham, Pino Orioli, Arthur Rubinstein, Osbert Lancaster, Rebecca West, Roger Senhouse, D'Arcy Thompson and others. Includes penned sketches throughout.
    - Notebook in the hand of Islay Lyons, 26 pages, circa 1950s (Box 61)
      Contains notes on archaeological sites in Bali, India, Pakistan, and Indonesia.
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings with Islay Lyons' contributions, maps, menus, sketches and ephemera, 1935-1980s (Box 61)
  - Oversize
    - Proof sheets and negatives, black and white and color, 1975-1978 (Box 64 (Oversize))
    - Assorted photographs, black and white and color, undated; 4 folders (Box 64 (Oversize))
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings with Islay Lyons' contributions, maps, menus, sketches and ephemera, 1935-1980s (Box 64 (Oversize))